<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jacob's Blograhams</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/feeds%5Clife.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jabrahams.ca/</id><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated><entry><title>Coffee And Me: A Complicated Romance</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/caffeine.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>Jacob Abrahams</name></author><id>tag:jabrahams.ca,2019-01-01:caffeine.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a tale in two parts about how I quit, then subsequently un-quit, caffeine, and the glaringly-obvious-in-hindsight-yet-still-meaningful things I learned about my brain along the way. Come with me and find out some facts anyone with a passing understanding of even the simplest parts of neurobiology could tell you, all of which I found out after &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; separate month-long adjustment periods and a hell of a lot of &lt;em&gt;arguably avoidable&lt;/em&gt; strife. It'll be fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part 1: Oct 2015 - Mar 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months after I started full-time at &lt;code&gt;BIG_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt;, I participated in a blood drive they were hosting on campus. This was nothing new for me - giving blood is one of my favourite forms of charity [1], and I'd done it roughly five times in the previous few years. What &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; new was something the technicians warned me about: my blood pressure was pretty dangerously high for an otherwise-healthy young adult male, around 150 systolic as I recall. I'd had problems with blood pressure (among other things) during my less-than-healthy (read: fat) pubescence, but this wasn't pudgy-short Jacob, this was &lt;em&gt;just-biked-across-fucking-Europe&lt;/em&gt; Jacob! Something was clearly out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The staff took my blood, but not before warning me to get a professional opinion from a doctor. Conveniently, there was one near work, but instead of that I treated the whole thing as I would a bug and Googled the quickest way to fix the problem. One module-at-the-top-of-the-search-results later, I'd narrowed down the potential causes to the following candidates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alcohol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greasy Food&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caffeine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eliminated the first three as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was currently the least-stressed I'd be in my entire professional life (at least at the time of this writing), because I was treating my job as I had treated my internships and the &lt;em&gt;horrendous downsides of doing that&lt;/em&gt; wouldn't become clear to me for a few months yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'd already cut down harshly on my drinking a few months prior, and doing more would just hurt me socially at that point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Probably&lt;/em&gt; valid, but &lt;code&gt;BIG_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt; food was so good, I'd rather just have the high blood pressure, thanks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic deduction therefore left caffeine as the only possible culprit [2]. I may have already been considering this as the culprit before my extremely detailed research (read: a Google search which was lazy even by Google search standards) because at the time of the measurement I was drinking, on average, 4 coffees per day, half of which would be sugary varieties like Mochas. I knew this wasn't &lt;em&gt;good for me&lt;/em&gt; per se, but until now I hadn't realized that it was &lt;em&gt;actively bad for me&lt;/em&gt;. So I did the only reasonable thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut out caffeine. All of it, all at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bet you're going, "Yeah, but you were drinking coffee again within the month, I bet."  Keep in mind, I'd had a love-hate-abuse-quit-relapse relationship with coffee for the better part of a decade at this point, and this wasn't my first time "quitting forever",  so even &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; had that reaction. But I was wrong, and so are you. I stuck to this dumbass idea for &lt;em&gt;over two years&lt;/em&gt;, and I didn't even really feel tempted to break away from it until a few days before I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're wondering, here's my "Super Effective, Guaranteed to Work (Or Maybe Kill You In the Process) Cold Turkey Method For Quitting Caffeine" (patent pending), in case you want to reproduce my results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't drink coffee. This may come across as obvious, but I mean &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; coffee. No decaf, no chocolate-covered coffee beans, nothing coffee flavoured. It'll just make you realize how much worse whatever you're consuming is than the real thing, and then it's all over for you. Hell, I even stayed away from tiramisu for a while, because I was so committed to this aspect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't drink tea. This is a good rule for two reasons: first, a lot of tea is caffeinated to some degree (and hence kind of against the point), and second, tea is just &lt;em&gt;worse coffee&lt;/em&gt; if we're being perfectly honest, which means we run into the same reasoning as we did with decaf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't drink &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; hot beverages for the first month. This goes along the same rationale as the previous points, but is a hell of a lot harder, especially when you occasionally live in a cold climate, where the relief of hot chocolate is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; tempting (luckily, I &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; avoided this by spending the first few months of the experiment in the land of unreasonable sun).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to obsessively drinking water. Smokers and former alcoholics usually pick up a new habit to fill the void, so make yours a healthy one. It won't wake you up quite the same way, but you can pretend it does!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last a month, and you're probably permanently good! Survive a trip over to a remote office in Great Britain where you don't sleep on the plane (as I &lt;em&gt;intelligently decided&lt;/em&gt; to do) and are therefore a zombie for half the time you're away, and you'll probably forget coffee exists!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say, my timing could have been better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, I persevered, and stuck to my guns rejecting the one substance that had been a source of joy for me since my early teens. While it didn't &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; end up lowering my blood pressure [3], I did notice an interesting range of effects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As long as I kept my sleep schedule consistent, even if it was incredibly poorly-reasoned and unnatural [4], sticking to it was basically trivial because suddenly my energy levels naturally followed a static, unchanging curve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My general anxiety levels, which had been middling for a few years at this point, dropped sharply and pretty much constantly stayed low. [5]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was drinking a lot more water to compensate, and water's generally got a ton of good side effects (better digestion, clearer skin, lower heartrate, not dying of dehydration, etc.), up until the point where you're actually drowning and the only side effect is "water in lungs"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, all of those things paled in comparison to the effect this whole thing had on my mood. If you've read any of my not-about-forks blog posts, you'll know I've suffered from chronic depression for pretty much all of my adult life. In the couple of years prior to this change, it'd taken the following general form: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few months of barely affecting me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then a month or so where it &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; affected me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was bad for two reasons. First, it was unpredictable as fuck, so I had to account for both the possibility I'd be normal and the possibility I'd be &lt;em&gt;barely functional&lt;/em&gt; when trying to plan pretty much anything significant (which was suboptimal to say the least). Second, the down-spike segments were progressively getting &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; with each one, and I was handling them with unevenly successful methods even at the best of times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, it wasn't doing that. Instead, it looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A motivational lull lasting a few weeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...ramping up over the course of a few months...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...to a normal-ish level, lasting a few weeks again...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...which gradually descends over a few months back down to the low&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying, "Quitting Caffeine Cured My Depression." (It really didn't.) I'm saying, "Taking A Psychoactive Substance In High Doses Isn't Always Good For Mental Stability." Quitting caffeine turned off the problems with my depression's cycle &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;, making it less dangerous and more predictable all at once. Now, I knew with reasonable certainty when I'd be functioning like my normal self, and when I wasn't able to do that I knew roughly how long I'd have to pretend. Success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last reason is why I stuck with the whole no-caffeine thing as long as I did. Fuck getting up at 5AM reliably, fuck blood pressure, and fuck healthy consumption habits. Predictable mental states are my &lt;em&gt;jam&lt;/em&gt;, son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't really see any downsides to all of this. It'd take a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of shit to go down before I would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part 2: Apr 2017 - Dec 2017 and onward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can hear you asking, "Why did you cut up the time periods like this? You said you stuck to this plan for over two years, but the first one is less than two years long. Plus the end of this part doesn't really make any sense since it's simultaneously a year ago and nonexistent, so what gives?" First off, that's a really detailed question, and I'm glad you're paying attention. Second off, I don't tell you how to do whatever you're doing right now [6], so don't tell me how to define my time ranges. Third, these time ranges correspond not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; to my experiences to "everyone's favourite substance violating the 'I before E' rule," but also experiences in my professional life: in March of 2017 I left &lt;code&gt;BIG_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt; and moved back to Toronto, and I joined &lt;code&gt;SMALL_STARTUP&lt;/code&gt; a month later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in September, I got fired. Whoops!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want to detract from the subject by getting into this in depth (trust me, I've had a blog post brewing on that topic for &lt;em&gt;over a year&lt;/em&gt; at this point), but if I can sum up some of the personal lessons I learned from all this, it would go like this: at &lt;code&gt;SMALL_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt;, I'd spent most of the time unmotivated, easily distracted and slow to accomplish most substantial things, slower to communicate, and even &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; to correct course on any of this. This didn't necessarily &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; a toxic relationship with my superiors, but it certainly didn't help when one started to develop. [7]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm, low motivation, low emotional energy, low mood? Why does that sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I described the top level of the new arc my depression followed as "normal-ish"? Turns out, that "ish" is pretty important. Despite having a more-or-less even emotional temperment now, it had a &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; centre than ever before, and was less resistant to things that dropped that further. (While maybe also being more resistant to factors that raised it? Hard to say.) I can think of a &lt;em&gt;bunch&lt;/em&gt; of reasons why this suddenly became a factor when it hadn't been in the past:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big companies have a lot more structure than small ones, and leaning on structure means that you always have a clear next step, so low motivation doesn't generally hurt as bad. [8][9]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big companies have constant weekly check-ins and quarterly goals to hit. Smaller ones just expect you to get shit done without any of that guidance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being in a small satellite office of a small company means there aren't as many people around to siphon social energy off of [10], which I find recharges me despite being vastly more introverted than the general population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things were kind of going to hell in my personal life, I was less fulfilled in my current role at work, and I'd stopped exercising and eating healthy the moment it became inconvenient, so a bunch of extraneous factors were pushing down on my mood &lt;em&gt;really hard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colder, darker climates are harder to function in. I know there's &lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/seasonal-affective-disorder/symptoms-causes/syc-20364651"&gt;a term&lt;/a&gt; for that, but I'm not one to self-diagnose. [11]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, after all this, I didn't even consider going back to caffeine at first. Clearly it had been a factor, but despite it all, I was happier without it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward two months of moping, working out, and drinking heavily at a Cuban all-inclusive [12]. I've gotten back up, gussied myself up a bit, and interviewed around in the slightly sparse (and suprisingly interconnected) Toronto tech scene. In the process, I've narrowed my next move down to three offers I have on the table, and after several days thinking it over, one of them is pushing me for an answer, like, &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;. In trying to push my brain to function at high capacity, I realize that, while swimming passively along with my brain's natural currents is fine for some things, I need a &lt;em&gt;surfable wave&lt;/em&gt; right now to get shit done. After struggling with the new meta-decision facing me for &lt;em&gt;hours&lt;/em&gt;, I decide what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need a coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After wandering up and down Roncesvalles Ave in Toronto for a good hour, I go to a cute little Polish bakery near the South end of the road, and get a Medium Dark Roast [13]. After a few hours and several whiteboards of Pros and Cons later [14], I'm able to make a decision [15]. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you, blessed caffeine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, I grab a cup every few days, finding comfort in the lightened version of my old routines. Later, when I start at the job I selected, I ramp up to my old two-to-three-a-day habit. I then have to &lt;em&gt;tweak&lt;/em&gt; this slightly, because I got old and now can't sleep properly if I drink coffee after dark. (Human biology: it sucks sometimes!) Apart from that, I've stuck to the new schedule &lt;em&gt;pretty much&lt;/em&gt; unchanged since, with occasional rest days to let my brain chemicals reset. In the process, I've noticed a few things I thought were negatives, but are actually subtle tradeoffs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember how I said I didn't get anxious anymore, but my general mood was lower? Turns out, you sort of trade one against the other: higher energy and higher volatility naturally go hand in hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You also make a tradeoff on &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you want your energy levels: even but predictable, or not-necessarily-predictable but available-on-demand. The first one is better for &lt;em&gt;planning&lt;/em&gt; around, the second is way better at &lt;em&gt;reacting&lt;/em&gt; to the unpredictable. &lt;code&gt;BIG_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt; was fine with the first, but startups really need the second.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the same time, the mood stability didn't really go away. Maybe I was just jumping to conclusions and shouldn't have been making assumptions during a time when I'd recently been &lt;em&gt;super depressed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fun fact: you can drink coffee &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; water! No need to quit your vice for that, you can glean the benefits of both at the same time!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where does that leave us? Well, it's 11:30pm on a Tuesday and I had to stay up late the night before (fucking New Years, worst holiday). Without coffee, I'd be unable to do anything more than browse my phone in bed (or, y'know, sleep). Instead, I'm writing this conclusion to an article that I've been meaning to write for months but never got around to, and I have a late-afternoon Mocha to thank for that. What we choose to put in our bodies is always some kind of tradeoff: food that's healthy is often devoid of joy, alcohol makes people bearable but the next morning less so, and most of the other things we enjoy just serve to hurt us in some way or another. Caffeine is no different here. [16]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really just comes down to a choice: do you want to ride the waves or try to guide them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]: It's free, relatively quick, and &lt;em&gt;metal as fuck&lt;/em&gt;. Plus they give you a cookie and juice!
[2]: Basic deduction would end up being wrong. When I did &lt;em&gt;eventually&lt;/em&gt; go to a doctor about all this, the cause they deduced was that I get mild anxiety from medical procedures (like, say, having my blood pressure taken), and that was messing up my vitals. Turns out, the internet is no substitute for good healthcare. Go figure.
[3]: See point 2. I'm only a few rungs above people who rely on WebMD. 
[4]: It was. Partially to keep more-in-sync with the East coast (where my family and girlfriend lived), partially to avoid horrendous Bay Area traffic, and partially just because, I'd committed to being out the door by 6AM every workday, and I managed to keep that up the entire time I lived in SF. Nowadays, the mere idea of that baffles me, and I sometimes can't get out of bed at 8AM. Brains are weird!
[5]: In retrospect, a) this should have been an obvious consequence, and b) this really should've tipped me off to [2] a lot sooner than it did. Whoops.
[6]: Despite the fact that I can hear you ask this, I can't actually see what you're doing. My apologies.
[7]: Another big factor, which I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; mention despite being besides the point: I joined &lt;code&gt;SMALL_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt; not primarily because of the people or the tech, but rather because they were located in SF, along with my social circle, but were opening a satellite in Toronto, where I was moving. Whenever asked for reasons why I joined in interviews, I absolutely &lt;em&gt;struggled&lt;/em&gt; not to mention this one first. Pro-tip: logistics is not a good main reason to join a company.
[8]: I'm generalizing a bunch here, obviously, and learning to self-structure is a huge thing I picked up from this experience, on top of everything else.
[9]: There actually &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a time where low motivation almost fucked me over at &lt;code&gt;BIG_COMPANY&lt;/code&gt;, but I didn't connect that to this until...just about now?
[10]: For most of my time there, there was &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; other person. 
[11]: My depression isn't self-diagnosed, for the record.
[12]: Some of which were healthier than others, obviously.
[13]: Sadly, I think this place has gone under since I moved. One time, they had what I would go on to describe as some of the most perfect croissants I've ever experienced (and I know my croissants). The next, they had the crappy ones that are basically just dishonest bread. I'll chock up their failure to the croissants.
[14]: Sometimes I'm more of a stereotypical engineer than I mean to be.
[15]: I'm still at this company at the time of this writing (just over a year later), so it could have been a worse decision I guess?
[16]: Also it cannot be stressed enough: &lt;strong&gt;THE INTERNET IS NO SUBSTITUTE FOR A MEDICAL OPINION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="coffee"></category><category term="mental health"></category><category term="nerdish"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>When Failsafes Fail</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/failsafes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>Jacob Abrahams</name></author><id>tag:jabrahams.ca,2014-03-08:failsafes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: this post is heavily personal, and not exactly cheery. It's also probably the most honest thing I will ever post on this blog, and easily the least emotionally-restrained. It has a lot of not-well-known info about me and my life that I've never been comfortable sharing. Depending on who you are and how well you know me, it may change the tenor of our interaction, and not necessarily for the better. Stop here if you aren't okay with that, or think I wouldn't be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still reading? Alright, you've been warned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about the effects and truths of depression and related mental illnesses, from a first- and second-hand perspective. I'll start by going over why I have whatever knowledge I do, since otherwise I'd just be talking out my ass. Then I'll go over the most important things to remember about this kind of stuff, basically a fact-or-myth about dealing with depression. I'll finish up with some opinions about more general handling of mental health issues, because what's a blog without opinion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background Info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never told this to anyone without a medical degree, but in March 2012 I was diagnosed with mild-to-moderate depression. Though this was aggravated by a borderline case of anaemia, there's some evidence to suggest I've been dealing with depression since I was a pre-teen, most notably some hereditary predisposition and, oh yeah, &lt;em&gt;the fact that I'm still suffering from it&lt;/em&gt;. Mild-to-moderate depression is basically what we'd call "high-functioning" if I were an alcoholic: it doesn't strongly affect how I go about my day-to-day life (&lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt;), but it can still lead to significant problems down the road. What it basically boils down to is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;little or no motivation to do pretty much anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extremely low social energy at times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tendency towards self-defeating thought processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a few other things I won't discuss here because my blog is public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I don't want to even fathom the number of people who read that section and went, "&lt;em&gt;Oh.&lt;/em&gt; That explains a lot.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I never tell anyone? Well, &lt;em&gt;have you met me&lt;/em&gt;? Do I seem like the type to ask outside myself for help? Do I seem like the type to &lt;em&gt;stop and admit that something is wrong&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I'm doing my best to change that, now. (This post might not stay up forever.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"But Jacob," you might say if you skipped the rest of this section, "you talk about severe depression later on. Surely you can't be as informed about that."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Get this section approved --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd respond with this ever-so-slightly more public information. In October 2010, I started dating a wonderful woman named Monica Post. This was somewhat against my better judgement because, while I was almost certain that I was madly in love with her, I was more certain that she was severely depressed, because I'd been one of the people to help her out of a particularly low point. Later we found out that she had Bipolar Disorder, an illness that is characterized by unpredictable shifts between periods of mania (over-confidence, delusions of grandeur, hyperactivity, hallucinations, psychosis, and general emotional instability) and periods of depression (which I described above, except stronger). In a move seen by those who knew as uncharacteristically mature and brave (I don't share this belief), I stayed by her for a little over three years, through the best times and the worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wish I didn't have to write in past tense. Monica died just under 4 months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside:I've never openly written on this subject without some level of control over my audience. My level of "handling it" fluctuates from day to day. On the better days, I want the subject as far away from me as possible. On the worse ones, I'm not strong enough to write about it. This blog post is partially me saying, "Fuck that. I'm stronger than this." (Before you agree with me, keep in mind that I had to write this section in private because I'm shaking like a poorly-built house on a fault line.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So uh yeah. Life experience is a bitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Or as close to facts as I can get)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, something I feel should always be mentioned: depression is mostly about chemical imbalances in the brain. If there's anything that bugs knowledgeable people the most, it's when people say to just "Get over it." Seriously, fuck you. That's like telling a person in a wheelchair to just get up and walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's go over some treatment methods. The "simplest" treatment is psychotherapy, or, if you're in a lazy work of fiction, "lie down on a couch with a guy who looks like Freud and talk about your mother." The current main school of thought is &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_behavioral_therapy"&gt;Cognitive Behavioural Therapy&lt;/a&gt;, which focuses on harmful thought processes and destructive emotional responses. I say "main", but from what I've experienced I could also easily say "only," because I've never seen any other kind of psychotherapy suggested. In programming terms, CBT (as it's almost always abbreviated) is debugging your mind: constantly thinking, "Why did I think that? Where did that emotional outburst come from? Why am I so affected by this?" Luckily, most people are better at this than &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt;, since it's been shown to be fairly effective on anything short of severe depression (not to mention many other kinds of mental illness.) Hell, I'd say depression-free people can even benefit from it from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sometimes it just doesn't work. You'd be surprised at how self-defeating a person with depression can be, and sometimes it's just too deeply-rooted in their thought process to be dislodged like that. Or it just takes too much energy, and depression takes enough away on its own. For that, medication is the next best thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I said depression is mainly chemicals? See, brains are &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. There's so much that can go wrong, and, even when it looks like the same thing is wrong in two people, they may not be helped by the same thing. Again, in CS-y terms, it's like supporting an Android app on every phone: there are so many subtle differences in hardware and the implementation of software that a bugfix on one platform is nowhere near guaranteed to work on all others. Hell, it might make things &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;. That's why there are so many anti-depressants out there, and that's why some people spend their entire life finding the right one. (Ignore the implications of the wording. That's not what I meant.) Prozac might work for you, or it might make you more suicidal. Effexor might make you a little brighter, or it might numb your emotions. Cymbalta might make you more stable or (also likely) less. But, of course, SSRIs don't work that fast, so you won't know until 4 weeks in, and by then you'll be experiencing all the &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; side-effects, and you'll probably go through withdrawal if it turns out it wasn't even working. Then you just repeat the process the next time you can see your psychiatrist, because, wow, it looks like they're booked &lt;em&gt;through until December&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, that's a bit of a raw nerve. Back on topic...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more extreme cures and fixes than medication and thought-correction, but I won't go into them here because I &lt;em&gt;won't&lt;/em&gt; be able to write about them while staying in a stable frame of mind. There are also less-extreme things that help. A huge factor, for instance, is proper physical health. I've noticed personally that it's easier to handle my symptoms when I've been keeping up a healthy routine of diet and exercise (though maintaining that through an episode isn't easy, to say the least). Obviously this isn't a cure, since the episodes still happen, but it has been shown to improve the stress reaction, which I think is the most important factor in getting through it. (&lt;a href="http://www.webmd.com/depression/guide/exercise-depression"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) To put this in nerd-terms, this goes about as far towards computer performance as keeping your fan free of dust: it won't fix a crashed hard-drive, but it'll help out at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to begin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start off at the obvious: please treat people with depression (and any other mental illness) as &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. Like, they aren't animals in a zoo or something, nor are they that mask of tragedy that hangs along its creepy-smile companion over every middle school drama department. They have just as much depth to their emotional state as any other person, and they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don't like to be labelled. I know the party-line is always about "removing stigma," but I feel like a lot of people who talk like that do very little to actually &lt;em&gt;remove&lt;/em&gt; it, and in some ways actually &lt;em&gt;further&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that note, the idea of a "mental health rally?" Stop. The last thing a depressed person wants is to be reminded of it in public. Further, you're making a social event &lt;em&gt;for people with no energy for social activity&lt;/em&gt;. How does that make sense? Making people aware of resources available to them is one thing. Pointing out what's &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; in a public setting is another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're having trouble, &lt;em&gt;see a therapist at least once&lt;/em&gt;. I'm not saying to sign up for 10 sessions, just see if it helps and go from there. If you want a resource on CBT for some self-study, I found &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mind-Over-Mood-Change-Changing/dp/0898621283"&gt;Mind over Mood&lt;/a&gt; to be pretty helpful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, don't suffer in silence. Don't wait 10 years to tell your family you think something is wrong. Maybe don't blog about it, but talking to someone, &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;, will help, trust me. I'm probably pushing the blog-barrier again, but that's one of the things I miss most, which is likely why I'm writing about it now, as opposed to months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy 3rd post! I'm going to go sit in my room for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="personal"></category><category term="mental health"></category><category term="heavy"></category></entry><entry><title>Eulogy</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/eulogy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>Jacob Abrahams</name></author><id>tag:jabrahams.ca,2013-11-18:eulogy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Note: I've re-dated this article so it doesn't turn up at the top of the page anymore. As you might tell from context, it was written a year after the publish date. Sorry for the confusion.&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never really did say a proper eulogy for Monica. I mean, sure, I said something at the service, and I guess it sufficed. I couldn't &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, not after what I'd shared with her, not with the raw pain I felt that day. My memory's a little broken (like everything else), but I remember bits and pieces of what I said, or set out to say, with my already-lacking public speaking skill set ever lower by circumstance. Something about having hoped to gather everyone in a church for a much happier reason. Something about how she'd lit up everyone's life. Something about her insisting on making gingerbread at 2AM one night when were supposed to be packing to leave our apartment for two weeks. Something about making too much gingerbread dough and most of it going bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I can do better. I'm a writer, after all, not a speaker. It's only a year late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me first share a story that was shared with me a few years back. This is way back, around the time Monica was 3 or 4 if I recall correctly. Her family was on vacation somewhere seaside, and her mom was watching over her somewhere on a beach. And Monica was intent on swimming. "Monica swim," she insisted. No, she was told, you're too little. "Monica swim," she replied, adamant. No, she was instructed, you'll fall. "Monica swim," she said one last time, and walked off to the water. Of course, she immediately fell in, but her mom was right there to pluck her out of the water to safety. As she spat out the saltwater, she had one last thing to say: "Monica no swim."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this shows the first thing a lot of people notice about her. Even when she was too young to understand grammar or tides, she still had this &lt;em&gt;determination&lt;/em&gt; to do what she thought needed to be done. She was one of the most determined people I knew, rarely letting anything get in the way of her goals. Sometimes, sure, she'd get in over her head, but she always managed to get plucked out out of the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I think of the Monica I knew, the woman she was with me, the memories that stick with me are always the same. Sometimes, when she was feeling sad or anxious, she'd lay her head in my lap and ask me to stroke her hair until she fell asleep. I can still feel the back of her head across my thighs, her soft hair around my fingertips. In my dreams, I can still see the look in her eyes change from distressed to calm to restful, still feel the love in them behind it all as she gazed up at me. I'd usually start to fall asleep before she would, so we usually wouldn't stay like that. She asked me once if I was bored of it, but the problem was the complete opposite: looking down at her, as I held her safe, I couldn't help but be at peace with the world, because no matter what, there was at least one thing right with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the phrase "better half" is overused when it comes to significant others, but I firmly believe it here: she was the missing piece of my two-piece puzzle, and she was definitely the better piece. I can't even begin to describe what she was to me, what she was to others, without feeling like I'm repeating myself. Everything she was part of felt better for it. She brought a vibrancy and energy I can't even comprehend to everything she did. She cared genuinely, and rarely if ever had a bad thing to say about anyone. She was always on the move, always curious about the next thing, always dreaming up new ideas and scheming new plans, and I loved her so much for it. I could share a thousand more stories, each one more and more &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt;, because there was always a new thing to be done, a new journey to be started, and I'm just so grateful for being taken along on every single one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That she was so friendly and caring and loving was something special in itself, but that she was all that despite the hand life had dealt her, despite her circumstance and struggles, was absolutely unheard of. Not only did the world lose a bright light the day she died, it lost one that was all the brighter for the darkness that surrounded it, and I don't think it can ever truly recover that. I think a little bit of everyone that knew her died when they heard. For some of us, it was more than a little. The world is a painful place indeed when the images and thoughts you once looked to for strength, for comfort, for support, now only offer a profound agony cutting through the core of your being. I never knew I could love someone so much that it would hurt this bad when I lost them, but that's just the kind of person Monica was, and that's just the effect she had on people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will never be enough. There will never be enough words to express what she was to me, what she was to our family, what she was to her friends and mine. I could never run through all the stories we lived during our time together, the eternities we shared in our few, far-too-short years together. But I hope this is enough to remind those who knew her of their own Monica stories, of their own memories of times with her. And I hope it's enough for those who didn't know her to understand what the rest of us are missing, why we hurt so bad even a year later. And I hope it'd be enough for her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Jacob&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Monica"></category></entry></feed>