<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jacob's Blograhams</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/feeds%5Clife.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jabrahams.ca/</id><updated>2014-03-24T00:00:00Z</updated><entry><title>Self-Respect and Actualization</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/respect-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-24T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>JacobAbrahams</name></author><id>tag:jabrahams.ca,2014-03-24:respect-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;(Note: this post was delayed for a few reasons, not the least of which was a desperately needed rewrite.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those keeping track at home, this is Part 2 of the series I started &lt;a href="/pride.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In its way, it's also Part 1 (of 3, I think) of a subseries inside the series based on a common theme. Yes, this is confusing, and yes, this adds up to 4 instead of 3 (as previously stated). If you look at the revision history on Github, the page actually said 4 for a while, which I changed once when planning things and won't change back because &lt;em&gt;stop telling me what to do&lt;/em&gt;. Now if you don't mind, let's get to the actual content...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd originally planned for this article to focus on respect, which is a pretty amorphous and vague term in a lot of ways. Respect for whom? How are you showing it? To what extent? Most importantly, &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are you showing respect? If you combine all the possible combinations of answers, you get...well, way more topics than I have energy to write about. Knowing my SQL, I decided to &lt;code&gt;GROUP BY target&lt;/code&gt;, because it flows nicely. (I'm aware you wouldn't put this information into a database. Stop nitpicking.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll start off with the person you know best: you. Without exception, you're the person you spend the most time with. You've also known you since before kindergarten, you've grown up with you, you've seen you naked, and (barring unforseen circumstances) you'll grow old with you. If you have to put up with you all this time, why not at least pay you &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; respect? I'll explain how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a person you deserve to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't think for a second that I mean you're entitled to higher pay (though you might be), or to win the lottery (though you might), or to violate physical laws (you won't). I mean, every person is a collection of values, experiences, and brain chemistry that make up what they are. These reflect in our personality and actions, which in turn affect all of them in this beautiful feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there's no reason not to make the person you deserve better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month ago or so, I was wondering how I was still standing. I could let circumstances take over. I could yield to my condition. I could put up all my old walls and shells and seal everything away. There were so many ways I could put things together and come out with a wrong result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I didn't. I kept moving, because despite it all I'd &lt;em&gt;earned&lt;/em&gt; the characteristics I'd needed to keep going. I'd earned the strength to go on from putting up with everything for so many years. I'd earned the tricks and hotfixes I use with the years I'd invested in developing them. I'd earned the emotional openness by making it through the most emotionally raw period in my life more-or-less intact. And I couldn't throw that effort, that investment, that &lt;em&gt;self-dedication&lt;/em&gt;, away. Because I &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; to be someone who got through it all. I have to keep trying to &lt;a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/EarnYourHappyEnding"&gt;earn my happy ending&lt;/a&gt;, not because I'm an optimist, not because I have any reason to believe everything will be alright, but because it's what I deserve to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you know what? It's what you deserve too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a life out there&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it's gonna be mine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;cite&gt;Train&lt;/cite&gt; (3 Doors Down)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="mental health"></category><category term="heavy"></category></entry><entry><title>Pride and Self-Image</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/pride.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-14T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>Jacob Abrahams</name></author><id>tag:jabrahams.ca,2014-03-14:pride.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I got an interesting response out of my last article. I'm not going to lie, it wasn't the easiest thing in the world to write, and it's kind of gratifying that it didn't fall on deaf ears. I got some great advice in exchange for the words I gave, and a lot of stories I obviously won't talk about at length. Sometimes it's nice to feel like you're not going at something alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the advice of my good friend &lt;a href="http://sandymaguire.me/"&gt;Sandy&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to quantify my motivators using a technique called &lt;a href="http://sandymaguire.me/goal-factoring/"&gt;goal-factoring&lt;/a&gt;. He's got an explanation there that's way better than anything I could come up with, but I'll make an attempt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by brainstorming your day-to-day activities. Ideally, this includess any conscious action, but if you can't remember something it's probably not going to factor in too much anyway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each activity, ask yourself &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you do it. Sometimes this makes sense, sometimes it doesn't, but don't stop thinking about it until you come up with at least one cause. In my case, I tried to generalize causes a little at this step to make the map cleaner, but you don't have to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Until you reach an obvious base level (eg. an emotion, a physical necessity), repeat with remaining roots from the previous step. You can update nodes to point to more base causes as necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He ends up with a chart that (from low-resolution) looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Goal-factoring Chart" src="/goalfactoring.jpg" title="Goal-Factoring Chart" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After drawing up my version of the process, I realized it wouldn't make as much sense as a chart for me for 2 reasons:
  * I can't draw. LaTeX? Still won't be readable (somehow). Some other charting software? Ain't nobody got time for that.
  * Mine turns out &lt;em&gt;so damn linear&lt;/em&gt; that it's a very simple ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by linear? Well it's simple: I came up with some 7 reasons why I do around 20 things I do. Out of these 7, 4 were linear compositions of the other 3. Out of the remaining 3, I could pinpoint some combination of 3 basic emotions. Then I stopped, because, as I said, there isn't much further to go from there, and the mathy part of me realized I'd found what amounted to the rank of my emotional matrix, so I probably wouldn't make further headway anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I ran into an issue: &lt;em&gt;what should I do with this information?&lt;/em&gt; I had no idea how to combine some vague sense of self-realization with a desire to write, a personal website, and so much unused creative energy. I thought long and hard on the issue, deliberated for hours, and...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just kidding. The moment I stopped writing out the list, I started thinking through the blog entries. This will be the first of three (if I'm lucky), and simultaneously the most and least upbeat. So here we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pride&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pride gets a bad rap. It's one of the deadly sins. It's associated with conceit, vanity, and self-interest. If you believe Quentin Tarantino, "Pride only hurts. It never helps."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also makes it possible to define yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain with an anecdote of sorts. Back in high school, I used to get around mostly by bike. (I still do, but I used to too.) By Grade 12, I had my route down perfectly: down along the lakeshore for about 7 km, then up one of the steepest hills in the city, then around 2 km more to my school's front entrance. It was a great path, stayed off the road for as long as possible, and had huge benefits for strength and cardio built right in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The waterfront was the hardest part. Large bodies of water tend to generate large air currents from convection, which means shorelines tend to be windy. Add in the fact that Lake Ontario is by no means small, and you get one hell of a windy bike ride. Most curiously, no matter what time I left and in which direction I was headed, the wind usually seemed to be &lt;em&gt;against me&lt;/em&gt;. So what did I do? Simple. I biked &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt;. It became so frequent that every time I felt a blast of wind along Lakeshore Boulevard West, I muttered under my breath:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring it on, motherfucker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, biking is something that I'd used to &lt;em&gt;define&lt;/em&gt; me. If I knew more philosophy, I'd say I considered biking to be &lt;em&gt;essential&lt;/em&gt; to my person. I claimed that route and made it mine. No one did it better. And no wind got in my way. Not backing down became vital to who I was, integrated firmly with my identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the kind of pride I mean. Not the harmful, get-in-your-way kind, but the kind that turns a simple activity like biking a short distance as fast as possible into a defense of your sense of self. The kind of feeling you get that makes you think, "I can't fail at this because it is not in my nature. &lt;em&gt;That is not who I am&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may still notice a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of pride can screw you over if you do end up failing at something you treasure. Suddenly, you're without part of your identity, and you don't know how to fix that. I'm going to go ahead and push my anecdote as far as I can to give you some tips on that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick your battles. I cannot stress this enough. Sure, biking into the wind made me feel validated because I could do it. But as it got colder? As the wind became less of a gentle, competitive shove and more of a threat on my life? As the streets iced up and the mornings grew dark? I stopped. I put my bike in the shed (&lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; hallway &lt;em&gt;coug&lt;/em&gt;) for the winter and went into my yearly trading-coffee-for-morning-rides phase. I knew I couldn't win against the elements, and, besides, I biked first and foremost because it made me feel &lt;em&gt;alive&lt;/em&gt;. Dying in the process wouldn't help anything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remind yourself periodically who's in charge. I have some rules about biking, like I try not to bike in the rain, and I avoid biking when I know I'll be out long after dark. Really, though, I just take a break from it every once in a while to remind me that I &lt;em&gt;chose&lt;/em&gt; to make it part of me, not the other way around. Remember, above all else, &lt;em&gt;you define you&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, let it drive you but keep your foot above the brake and your hands over the steering wheel (like you would with a self-driving car). And when you feel that gust pushing at you the exact moment you were starting to tire, lower your head, grin, and say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring it on, motherfucker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="mental health"></category><category term="heavy"></category></entry><entry><title>When Failsafes Fail</title><link href="http://jabrahams.ca/failsafes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>Jacob Abrahams</name></author><id>tag:jabrahams.ca,2014-03-08:failsafes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: this post is heavily personal, and not exactly cheery. It's also probably the most honest thing I will ever post on this blog, and easily the least emotionally-restrained. It has a lot of not-well-known info about me and my life that I've never been comfortable sharing. Depending on who you are and how well you know me, it may change the tenor of our interaction, and not necessarily for the better. Stop here if you aren't okay with that, or think I wouldn't be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still reading? Alright, you've been warned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about the effects and truths of depression and related mental illnesses, from a first- and second-hand perspective. I'll start by going over why I have whatever knowledge I do, since otherwise I'd just be talking out my ass. Then I'll go over the most important things to remember about this kind of stuff, basically a fact-or-myth about dealing with depression. I'll finish up with some opinions about more general handling of mental health issues, because what's a blog without opinion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background Info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never told this to anyone without a medical degree, but in March 2012 I was diagnosed with mild-to-moderate depression. Though this was aggravated by a borderline case of anaemia, there's some evidence to suggest I've been dealing with depression since I was a pre-teen, most notably some hereditary predisposition and, oh yeah, &lt;em&gt;the fact that I'm still suffering from it&lt;/em&gt;. Mild-to-moderate depression is basically what we'd call "high-functioning" if I were an alcoholic: it doesn't strongly affect how I go about my day-to-day life (&lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt;), but it can still lead to significant problems down the road. What it basically boils down to is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;little or no motivation to do pretty much anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extremely low social energy at times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tendency towards self-defeating thought processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a few other things I won't discuss here because my blog is public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I don't want to even fathom the number of people who read that section and went, "&lt;em&gt;Oh.&lt;/em&gt; That explains a lot.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I never tell anyone? Well, &lt;em&gt;have you met me&lt;/em&gt;? Do I seem like the type to ask outside myself for help? Do I seem like the type to &lt;em&gt;stop and admit that something is wrong&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I'm doing my best to change that, now. (This post might not stay up forever.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"But Jacob," you might say if you skipped the rest of this section, "you talk about severe depression later on. Surely you can't be as informed about that."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Get this section approved --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd respond with this ever-so-slightly more public information. In October 2010, I started dating a wonderful woman named Monica Post. This was somewhat against my better judgement because, while I was almost certain that I was madly in love with her, I was more certain that she was severely depressed, because I'd been one of the people to help her out of a particularly low point. Later we found out that she had Bipolar Disorder, an illness that is characterized by unpredictable shifts between periods of mania (over-confidence, delusions of grandeur, hyperactivity, hallucinations, psychosis, and general emotional instability) and periods of depression (which I described above, except stronger). In a move seen by those who knew as uncharacteristically mature and brave (I don't share this belief), I stayed by her for a little over three years, through the best times and the worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wish I didn't have to write in past tense. Monica died just under 4 months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside:I've never openly written on this subject without some level of control over my audience. My level of "handling it" fluctuates from day to day. On the better days, I want the subject as far away from me as possible. On the worse ones, I'm not strong enough to write about it. This blog post is partially me saying, "Fuck that. I'm stronger than this." (Before you agree with me, keep in mind that I had to write this section in private because I'm shaking like a poorly-built house on a fault line.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So uh yeah. Life experience is a bitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Or as close to facts as I can get)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, something I feel should always be mentioned: depression is mostly about chemical imbalances in the brain. If there's anything that bugs knowledgeable people the most, it's when people say to just "Get over it." Seriously, fuck you. That's like telling a person in a wheelchair to just get up and walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's go over some treatment methods. The "simplest" treatment is psychotherapy, or, if you're in a lazy work of fiction, "lie down on a couch with a guy who looks like Freud and talk about your mother." The current main school of thought is &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_behavioral_therapy"&gt;Cognitive Behavioural Therapy&lt;/a&gt;, which focuses on harmful thought processes and destructive emotional responses. I say "main", but from what I've experienced I could also easily say "only," because I've never seen any other kind of psychotherapy suggested. In programming terms, CBT (as it's almost always abbreviated) is debugging your mind: constantly thinking, "Why did I think that? Where did that emotional outburst come from? Why am I so affected by this?" Luckily, most people are better at this than &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt;, since it's been shown to be fairly effective on anything short of severe depression (not to mention many other kinds of mental illness.) Hell, I'd say depression-free people can even benefit from it from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sometimes it just doesn't work. You'd be surprised at how self-defeating a person with depression can be, and sometimes it's just too deeply-rooted in their thought process to be dislodged like that. Or it just takes too much energy, and depression takes enough away on its own. For that, medication is the next best thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I said depression is mainly chemicals? See, brains are &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. There's so much that can go wrong, and, even when it looks like the same thing is wrong in two people, they may not be helped by the same thing. Again, in CS-y terms, it's like supporting an Android app on every phone: there are so many subtle differences in hardware and the implementation of software that a bugfix on one platform is nowhere near guaranteed to work on all others. Hell, it might make things &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;. That's why there are so many anti-depressants out there, and that's why some people spend their entire life finding the right one. (Ignore the implications of the wording. That's not what I meant.) Prozac might work for you, or it might make you more suicidal. Effexor might make you a little brighter, or it might numb your emotions. Cymbalta might make you more stable or (also likely) less. But, of course, SSRIs don't work that fast, so you won't know until 4 weeks in, and by then you'll be experiencing all the &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; side-effects, and you'll probably go through withdrawal if it turns out it wasn't even working. Then you just repeat the process the next time you can see your psychiatrist, because, wow, it looks like they're booked &lt;em&gt;through until December&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, that's a bit of a raw nerve. Back on topic...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more extreme cures and fixes than medication and thought-correction, but I won't go into them here because I &lt;em&gt;won't&lt;/em&gt; be able to write about them while staying in a stable frame of mind. There are also less-extreme things that help. A huge factor, for instance, is proper physical health. I've noticed personally that it's easier to handle my symptoms when I've been keeping up a healthy routine of diet and exercise (though maintaining that through an episode isn't easy, to say the least). Obviously this isn't a cure, since the episodes still happen, but it has been shown to improve the stress reaction, which I think is the most important factor in getting through it. (&lt;a href="http://www.webmd.com/depression/guide/exercise-depression"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) To put this in nerd-terms, this goes about as far towards computer performance as keeping your fan free of dust: it won't fix a crashed hard-drive, but it'll help out at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to begin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start off at the obvious: please treat people with depression (and any other mental illness) as &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. Like, they aren't animals in a zoo or something, nor are they that mask of tragedy that hangs along its creepy-smile companion over every middle school drama department. They have just as much depth to their emotional state as any other person, and they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don't like to be labelled. I know the party-line is always about "removing stigma," but I feel like a lot of people who talk like that do very little to actually &lt;em&gt;remove&lt;/em&gt; it, and in some ways actually &lt;em&gt;further&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that note, the idea of a "mental health rally?" Stop. The last thing a depressed person wants is to be reminded of it in public. Further, you're making a social event &lt;em&gt;for people with no energy for social activity&lt;/em&gt;. How does that make sense? Making people aware of resources available to them is one thing. Pointing out what's &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; in a public setting is another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're having trouble, &lt;em&gt;see a therapist at least once&lt;/em&gt;. I'm not saying to sign up for 10 sessions, just see if it helps and go from there. If you want a resource on CBT for some self-study, I found &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mind-Over-Mood-Change-Changing/dp/0898621283"&gt;Mind over Mood&lt;/a&gt; to be pretty helpful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, don't suffer in silence. Don't wait 10 years to tell your family you think something is wrong. Maybe don't blog about it, but talking to someone, &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;, will help, trust me. I'm probably pushing the blog-barrier again, but that's one of the things I miss most, which is likely why I'm writing about it now, as opposed to months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy 3rd post! I'm going to go sit in my room for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="personal"></category><category term="mental health"></category><category term="heavy"></category></entry></feed>